the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
all right welcome to the stoa i am
peter limberg the steward of the stoa
and it still is a place for us to cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the nice edge
of this very moment and today jeremy
johnson
returns to the stoa um jeremy is an
editor and publisher of
revlor presh i think that's how you
pronounce it and liminal news
and he's the author of seeing through
the world gene gepser and integral
consciousness
and he's the host of mutations podcast
so a little bit a preface of how this
event came about
so i released this piece called the
artistic piece called the cancel god on
both high existence and rebel wisdom
and uh the feedback was you know some
people are like oh it's amazing
all this is shit and there's a segment
of a population that actually had uh
legitimate and good criticism
and uh mostly around the integral left
i would say and jeremy johnson was one
of them and so he tweeted something out
and invited him to the stoa to present
his thoughts
to us today um
and i i think jeremy will discuss what
it is but it's not just a critique on
the the piece that i did but a critique
on the whole
uh cancel culture critique from the
intellectual dark web and colette and
stuff like that
um and i don't publish much intellectual
content but when i do and there's good
critique on it
i would love for people to come in and
provide it
because the stoa is a place a public
square where
my hope is that we can transcend
tribalism
and have a good faith conversations um
so yeah that being said uh how it's
gonna work
is jeremy's gonna present his thoughts
um and if you have any questions
throw them in the chat box i imagine i
will i will talk to jeremy for a bit
uh and then i will call on you you'll
mute yourself ask your question to
jeremy
um if you want me to read your question
on your behalf just indicate that and
then i will read on your path because
this will be going on
youtube um so that being said i will
allow jeremy to unmute himself
and i hope you weren't too offended by
the intro song jeremy but uh i'll take
you in
no problem peter uh thanks for having me
on again thanks for the invitation i was
not offended
uh that song's perfectly fine doesn't
need to be cancelled
so yeah i mean a part of this is just
you know a good faith kind of engagement
with the video and some of the initial
ideas
you had sent it in a kind of a group dm
and there was a lot of playful banter
back and forth with the number of us who
were here
just about the using a metaphor of
of this this sort of uh archetypal
uh creepypasta style uh
internet tulpa or being right
the cancel god right and trying to
understand
cancel culture as a kind of a
theological structure of behavior um a
kind of
capture of religious imagination maybe
moving towards puritanism or
mind hijacking and obviously you know i
think
your own steel manning of the leftist
position was actually
quite coherent and clear enough that not
too much more needs to be said about
that specifically
i think generally speaking folks on the
left who did engage with you probably
had
similar critiques in terms of
wondering who this video was for in
terms of who it was addressing and how
it was
framing cancel culture so yes i think
for people who have criticisms of cancer
culture and feel that it is an outspoken
phenomenon
that it's a real problem um i think
they'd see that video and probably be
like okay
cool for a lot of folks on the left i
think there was a kind of a throwing up
of hands and i'm like
there's so much more we could talk about
here but rather than
engage with you in that way i thought it
would be fun to take that
metaphor of the canceled god and
flip it into a kind of gnostic metaphor
right
and that was part of our initial
exchange that the canceled god is really
a demiurge
right of some kind of deeper and i wrote
this in my
in my article a kind of uh catholic
uh um neoliberalism right that there is
a sort of substrata a sort of negative
theology of neoliberalism
that this particular social behavior
is a part of right and if we really want
to
borrowing that religious metaphor in
some sense uh
transcend cancel culture or
address in a really substantive way
the cultural polemics that are occurring
right now we need to actually go
beyond that demiurge right or trace that
demiurge into some deeper substratum
that is that has produced it right so
using that metaphor playfully
i took that as an opportunity to go okay
so we have
especially in the intellectual dark web
especially in a lot of circles
um that recently even in terms of like
leftist
liberals have been critiquing cancer
culture there's a kind of um
uh the onus is on cancel culture right
the onus is on
as ken wilber talks about mean green
meme and it's
it's uh eccentricities it's zealotry
it's puritanism etcetera is it's really
the
the kind of driver of some of this
cultural atomization it's making it very
difficult
to find some kind of integration process
and my critique is really saying
the symptom of mean green meme
or cancel culture is part of something
deeper
it's a deeper issue that we can look
into but it's part of this process of
cultural atomization that the left
is just as possessed by
as everybody else now maybe cancel
culture is the
expression or the deity or the demiurgic
mask of neoliberalism on the left on the
right we could say it's something else
and in culture in general i think we've
seen a systemic kind of atomization
taking place
not being able to build bridges
increasing siloization
fragmentation etc so why is that right
that's what i'm more interested in and
that's really um
where i think kind of a leftist critique
really needs to come
in because of well i brought up three
things and i'll just kind of go through
them in that order but the first
is recognizing and understanding having
a literacy about
the media ecological environment that we
all interact in
from zoom to twitter to facebook etc how
are these
social apparatus right these social
prosthetics
because in the age of of the pandemic
they're they're the primary means of us
communicating with one another
rather than being in face-to-face how
are these
social systems designed architected and
engineered
because if we look into a lot of the
studies and i mentioned douglas rushkoff
there's a number of
other great great books beyond team
human and uh
throwing rocks at the google bus that
show and demonstrate that these social
media
environments incentivize
hyperpolarization
and siloization this is a market
incentive it may not even be
like a kind of a conscious um
desire to polarize culture but these are
underlying market incentives that drive
the social architecture that we're all
swimming in
and recently there was as i mentioned a
great
zack stein uh podcast on emerge with
daniel thorson where they were talking
about this is just how explicit this
incentivization
of polarization and fragmentation is
online and rushkoff goes far enough to
say that it's anti-human right it
doesn't allow
the messiness of long-form conversation
the nuance and complexity to kind of
smooth out or perhaps co-inhabit
difference
right to see the complexity of these
questions and situations
it's a very like well cancel culture is
a great example of this let's condemn
this person they are
you know they're evil incarnate they
need to be shunned and exiled from
society or removed from social media or
they mean to lose their job et cetera
but the the other the other kind of
thing goes as well in terms of
on the left and the right we have all of
this constant straw manning of one
another
so this kind of and i'm using this word
from from gene gepser's work this sort
of perspectival
pinning down of the complexity and
nuance of the human
in these social environments is part of
the market incentive
for these social environments they're
making a lot of money doing this right
and selling our data etc so so that's
the first kind of literacy i think we
really need to be able to critique
cancel culture right like it's a
phenomena
in an environment that incentivizes
collective mob behavior polarization
hyper fragmentation the second turning
that i think
gives us a sort of a deeper material
historical analysis and historical
literacy is understanding that
okay digital markets and digital
capitalism is part of this longer
process
that we know on the left and call you
know it's called neoliberalism
but what does that actually mean and how
does that play into
the rise of um how we situate the the
left and the right today as
the left is claiming or that we claim
that the left
has won the culture war right they are
allowing pr firms to get woke their
um i think alex b in in one of his
recent rebel wisdom articles talked
about you know
if starbucks can have a pr firm about
you know
um uh a black lives matter then we're
kind of in trouble here because
there's this unholy alliance between i
think he calls it that
an unholy alliance between capitalism
and wokeness what's that about
right so that's sort of the the general
impression i think people have of the
left
left means wokeness it's not really
talking about
um as a as a realistic
goal some kind of structural
transformation of society it's just
looking for more
um more equity more um
more more freedom and then more ability
to participate
in the society that we already have so
when we look at the history of
neoliberalism over the past 35 40
years what we see is a systematic uh
failure admittedly of the left
to retain its power in labor right to
retain the power to be able to
bargain with corporations to have some
kind of
um uh economic and social sway on how
institutions and said economics
um uh translate into society and we've
seen this since the mark
the the thatcher reagan era in the 1980s
it really started in the 1970s with the
inflation
um and we see a kind of pivot of the
left from a labor
left which had an intersection of of
class and race
to a a move into
more of this fighting in the culture war
right so
there's obviously been an impotency in
the left in terms of class politics
and labor um and a lot of this has been
redirected towards culture
and there's been some tremendous gains
in that and i think this is sort of what
i mentioned
in the article as well is that um this
is not to
say that wokeness or fighting in the
culture war
that is that has become increasingly and
problematically separated from class
struggle
is somehow a lesser form of the left i
mean
no i think i think the gains have been
genuinely positive and i think the
internet and digital culture has enabled
us to some degree to
make those gains in a way we hadn't been
able to before
but now i think and especially we've
seen in the past four to five years
a tremendous awakening of the left and a
lot of questions about well
if we have no class consciousness
anymore if there is no labor
consciousness
if that is still eroded how do we
actually gain traction in movements like
black lives matter recently right so
i think we're looking at a a need to
synthesize
both this is again a gross
simplification of the woke left and the
class oriented left
synthesize these two forces bring them
together
if there's any critique i think in terms
of
wokeness on the internet right in a sort
of hyper-vigilant wokeness that
people have been i think appropriately
concerned about
i i believe this kind of problem would
be ameliorated
if we began to focus more on actually
gaining economic and social
legal structural power right not just
institutional power not just
representation in ceo boards not just
political correctness in corporations
and representation
but actual structural systemic and
economic redistribution
um that is the kind of power that really
needs to be re
reintroduced in the left and i think
they're trying to figure that out right
so i think those are the two very
important layers here
that need to be developed
as a competency if we're going to
critique the left if we're going to
critique cancel culture and wokeness we
have to see
what it stems from we have to see that
perhaps some of its over exaggerations
and hyper vigilance have been a result
of this kind of
impotency for actual structural
transformation
um and then as i mentioned in that tweet
thread too right like
in terms of the culture wars it's the
left
you know may have symbolically dominated
the conversation but
they haven't actually won the culture
war like ideologically
economically we are still functioning
and perhaps even more so
on the right than we ever have before so
you know i think we have to really kind
of make some important distinctions here
about what actually is going on with the
culture war
what the historical analysis the
material historical analysis right of
class politics
can inform us about that uh that
frustration
how that is also doubly right on the
other end has fueled
a lot of the reactionary politics that
we've seen crop up over the past 10
years or so
with increasing austerity and increasing
loss of labor in the united states et
cetera or
abroad so there's a lot to go in here
but this is why the left analysis has
really needed to be integrated right
like let's subsume
um what the left has to say about class
and race and the
intersectionality of those things and
the history of those things
before we take down a straw man about
okay wokeness is the real problem
there's these deeper historical forces
that are
um to strongly use the word producing
some of this cultural fragmentation
neoliberalism
and really like this is again where the
class analysis comes in and we we know
that the ideology of our economic system
is extractive it's atomizing it's
segmenting
it's it's unidirectional is one
directional in terms of growth right
um this process of of globalization
which we have seen
sort of hijacked economics over the past
30 40 years with neoliberalism
is part of the reason why we're seeing
this massive cultural breakdown right
now
and we might say that's not enough we
might say that there needs to be
an integral or a meta modern or a
systemic turn and say no no the problem
isn't just neoliberalism it's the whole
civilization
we need a game b et cetera i think
that's fine but
without this material analysis as one of
the foundational pillars of thinking
and literacy we're not really going to
be able to do much right if we don't
have a literacy about
um polarization and incentivized
polarization
in uh through the markets in digital
media in our social media environments
how are we going to combat that right if
we don't have a historical literacy of
neoliberalism
and the kind of economic stressors that
have fueled both
hypervigilant woke uh cancel culture
and reactionary
ethno you know uh uh reactionary you
know trumper kind of attitudes
then we're not going to be able to
really see through some of these
processes
that need to be ameliorated and the left
is an ally and i guess that's the thing
that i was
kind of concluding in those first two
sections the left becomes an
ally here if we can take that theory and
and wield it right use that analysis
appropriately
to work towards solutions to maybe
create alternative platforms on social
media to
amplify certain experimental economic
models
and etc so this is not to say everyone
needs to become leftist i think it's
just to say that
leftism in theory and practice has a lot
to teach us
right there's a lot to integrate for
folks who are more interested in
experimenting with
new paradigms and new models um
so the deeper they perhaps the kind of
the the finer final layer here at least
in the article
is taking this to the deeper substratum
the deeper cathodic
elements which have more to do with i
think what we're interested in
in a lot of the consciousness culture
which is
consciousness studies which is
phenomenology which is
what what is the ontology that produces
these forces of colonialism and
capitalism
or as as some folks have popularized the
phrase the capital low scene
what is the sense-making orientation
that our
culture has produced and inhabits
that is able to bring that form of
economic ideology
material social policy et cetera and
enact it
right and then how can we overcome that
in ourselves
in that very true kind of subjective
sense that phenomenological sense
to be able to imagine different
possibilities in the world
to enable ourselves to think both media
ecologically and to see these
environmental historical pressures
but not be reductive which i admit it is
a leftist i think there's a lot of
reductionism and anti-spirituality
to see that those um those insights are
equally as important for overcoming
capitalism and imagining a
post-capitalist future
right so those are the three kind of
literacies we have
again the market social media literacy
neoliberalism as a literacy
just sort of the history of that the
forces that have shaped
the contemporary day and age and then
the deeper history the history of
consciousness
in terms of how sense making has evolved
through cultural evolution to bring us
to where we are today
and i would say my final point about
that i have some differences about
wilbur because i think wilbur
in a post-truth world and a lot of his
analysis has been
on um just just not sufficiently
his theory hasn't been sufficiently used
to comment on what's going on
because he makes the same mistake he
blames it on mean
green meme as the leading the bleeding
edge pathology
that's causing all of these problems um
i will quickly mention
that i think of a more appropriate use
of his model
would be to situate a lot of what's
going on not in the pathologies of green
but a sort of arrested development
that's free for those who aren't
familiar with the terminology green is
like progressive it's leftist
you know uh there's an arrested
development at amber
or orange or modernistic stage for him
and what we really need to see is the
center of gravity moving more
into green the the kind of things that
amber used to do or modernism used to do
in terms of economics etc
that have been left alone for that stage
to do
need to move their center of gravity
into green like economics needs to be a
green thing green thing isn't just peace
and love and everybody's got to be equal
green is let us innovate economic and
social systems for better equity
and more resilience on the planet right
so green needs to kind of come of
age in that sense but amber is present
preventing that
and i think in many senses that is why
we see
i'm sorry i'm using amber i think i mean
orange i'm sorry the colors mixed they
used to be different
but modernism the modernistic stage
is holding everyone hostage we have the
reactionary pre-modern
sort of mythical entrenchment and then
we have the reactionary hyper-vigilant
green
but in the center is this center of
gravity
which takes the longest to change right
economics legal systems
civilizations this is the the the most
coagulated crystallized
i don't know what better word exfoliated
expression of consciousness like this is
this is it becoming a kind of
material environment for us right that's
the hardest to overcome
it's the hardest to transform and i
think that is what's
arresting everyone else and
pathologizing these these two
wielding um memetic oscillations between
mythic and then postmodern or green so
that's just the wilbur analysis if we
move again
this is where i'm coming from into
a sort of gebsarian analysis which looks
more at cultural phenomenology it's not
a stage centered
we still have this deep insight about um
not just neoliberalism but if we look at
the kind of phenomena that most of the
left from like mark fisher's acid
acid communism and capitalist realism
to a lot of other great thinkers that's
saying you know the
the capitalism is this atomizing force
that arrests
that ultimately arrests the production
of the new
uh we see the same kind of language that
gepser has as an insight for the
perspectival world for what he calls
perspectivalism
which he sees as this deeper again
historical process
of the cultural evolution really kind of
beginning
in the renaissance period the beginning
of modernity sort of beginning with this
cartesian split
um this atomization this ability or
capacity to make the cut
and to break forth out of that mythical
participatory membrane
of the unperspective or the pre-modern
world um
that's great to be able to do that to
make those measurements to
spatialize time to explore the
three-dimensional world to
develop the ego the sense of self and
itself and other
right but that mode of consciousness for
gepster has has already outlived itself
he says we need to move into this
integral mode of being in the world a
different ontology and a different
phenomenology but until we do what we're
going to see and i think we see this
today
and this is how i'm looping it back to
the bulk culture and the cancel culture
et cetera
what we're seeing today is how digital
media
um is for the time being still
captured by the perspective of a world
that atomization
like epster was writing this in 1949 he
was saying you know
um atomization is increasing there's
going to be basically a war
of all against all nobody's perspectives
will be able to jive with anybody else's
perspectives there's everything is
there's going to be
cultural breakdown right cultural
atomization
that's the end point that's sort of the
death expression of the perspectival
world
and he saw that as sort of the an ever
increasing
intensification of that in our cultural
phenomenology
that it would become increasingly
pressing and difficult
to cross these bridges so i think
to pause and sort of conclude here
what we really need perhaps is an
integral left
a left that understands the criticisms
that in
integrates the material analysis that
leftist politics and class theory
and intersectionality can offer us but
doesn't
stop there necessarily it adds and
introduces this deeper cultural
phenomenology
in the the becoming of consciousness to
enable
us to imagine what frank um franco
before berardi calls uh future ability
right
imagine the possible and how do we
countervail
a culture a neoliberal culture of hyper
atomization and fragmentation well
zack stein says we get offline we we
meet each other face to face maybe
that's hard right now
but there are other ways we can do this
right there are other ways like
chilhan talks about um cultivating the
via contemplativa in terms of becoming
more present
this is essentially what gepster
suggests as this sort of radical act of
becoming truly open to the present
and to each other in empathy and the
complexity of the present
now this allows us to in some sense to
overcome these
social material economic and also um
uh consciousness oriented crises that
are manifesting right now in both the
meaning crisis and the meta crisis
um so i would say like the an integral
left begins there somewhere it begins
with our ability to
become more present um to not
um to have equanimity towards our
allergies if we really feel
like the left is is um we feel kind of
reactionary or don't want to touch
leftist theory i think we have to i
think we really have to move into it
but do it in a way that is this more
equanimous
present and imminent attitude and when
we do that i think
you know at least individually we've
overcome
a culture of atomization if not
culturally right i think um it's
then we begin to cohere what the
integral world looks like or what
integrative thinking
or what um what the world after hyper
fragmentation atomization looks like if
we can begin to live that in the present
that is really our only shot that is
really our only chance
um so that's sort of my my whole my
whole spiel
right those three main points um
and we can we can open it up here and we
can we can start
dancing very cool yeah that was awesome
um
so if you have any questions for jeremy
put him in the chat now just indicate
highly question
in front of your question so i can like
you know determine if it's a question or
statement
um so i'll start off with one question
um
i'll actually kind of talk about the the
cancer culture piece a little bit that
kind of
inspired this this talk and then that
will lead into a question
um so somebody earlier in the chat said
what is the
like a a right version or conservative
version of cancel culture
and so just to kind of give you how the
sausage was made of that cancel that
piece
well for first people haven't read it it
was a short like a thousand word kind of
essay
and high existence then rebel wisdom did
a short video on it
the idea there is that through the
culture of cancellation and i use that
word
uh specifically well i'll say that in a
moment why uh a god emerge and now is to
god emerge that
wants to make everyone afraid to
actually talk and then if everyone's
afraid
uh to talk then everyone's at jeopardy
we're at risk of the medic crisis and
going extinct as a species that's the
general idea
um so how the sausage was made there
originally
i i was making the argument that every
memetic tribe whether from left or right
has their own version of a canceled
culture there's an in-group and an out
group
and through that that that god emerged
but the first essay people didn't like
it has two nuances and it's not
mythological there's a second essay they
didn't like a third essay then
through all that then like you know
getting exhausted just wanting to get
out there
cut a lot of stuff so propositionally
yeah it looked like the finger was being
pointed at uh sort of the
the woke social justice mean green meme
which was not my original intention but
it is something that
i did right and then the the rebel
wisdom piece was like three over three
hours of filming cut down to five
minutes a lot of nuance was cut
so i understand how it did read like
that and
as jeremy said in the newsletter i said
yeah this is ultimately
was didn't serve as this kind of super
ordinary meme that i was hoping for is
just going to get collapsed into
cultural
argument and this was the case so a guy
like mike cernovich retweeted it and a
bunch of like make-a-goons were tweeting
this i'm like oh god
um so i did uh admit confess to that
um so but that being said and you said i
still manda left this approach i think i
i agreed with it i didn't understand i
agreed with it uh in
the newsletter so my first question to
you uh
this this talk was called transcending
the cancel culture critique
and uh you know when people hear
transcending or at least the wilbur it's
like transcendent conclude
let's include a certain the good of of
what we're criticizing or we're talking
about i should say
um and i imagine people who are making
these sort of critiques against castle
culture they say all this guy's just
critiquing cancer culture he's not he's
not transcending it
um could you steel man the the cancel
culture critique
uh and maybe uh what's what's there a
value that can be included
before we transcend it yeah great
question
um yeah so i think for me
the best i can steal men at is is that
like
obviously like obviously right that
twitter dog piling and you know
attacking people
on the as a sort of collective mob for a
particular kind of behavior
definitely creates an environment where
where there is no possibility and this
is something that
you know my my friend recently passed
michael brooks talked about there is no
room for redemption
in a culture that really is is hyper
vigilantly looking for somebody to make
a mistake
and to take them down and of course the
argument against that is always
well the people that are being canceled
are rich celebrities and they don't need
our help
and they don't need a job etc i don't
really think that's necessarily the case
i think it's sort of
um it's just whoever right there there's
no particular target i think
celebrities have or maybe an easier
target um but i i don't think that is
conducive to a healthy environment
um now i will i will suggest that
there's some good arguments coming from
the left that defend this behavior and
say well okay there's some collateral in
that but
generally speaking people who've never
had a voice or any kind of social
um social clout or social empowerment
before
finally do right and they finally have
some kind of amplification
that the media certainly is not giving
them the media certainly you know
journalism certainly hasn't
up until very recently um sort of turned
towards a more
more receptive um uh especially well
this has been critiqued
the new york times et cetera but um
my response to that would be you know
that that is a good point
but what is the ultimate
end point of this is it to merely be
represented well in a deeply
pathological neoliberal system
in terms of you know being on a
corporate board and represented well et
cetera or having kind of a pr
firm um that goes around in capitalism
teaching people to be
much more equitable in their social
behavior policing that like
obviously that's not all we want we want
a society that is fundamentally
transformed
um so i think i think there are
the the result of cancel culture as a
whole
creates an environment that is
fundamentally unredemptive
right and the the capacity to
make mistakes and be human right is
is not possible in a culture that is
predominantly
you know looking to cancel people and
cancel them out forever right
so i i would like to see and that that
would be a a
an attempt to steal man the critique
against cancel culture is that like yeah
the kind of consciousness that produces
is is ultimately
um is ultimately anti-human
because to be human is to be deeply
flawed
to make mistakes and to hopefully at
some point
come around with empathy and if they
don't that's another
case right like i think there are some
situations where
maybe somebody should be shamed out of
public office for for
some really horrendous kind of
commentary or
something along those lines um but it's
a slippery slope to go down that
route and i know there's the there's the
the liberal critique
uh which is the other kind of steel man
a lot of people say like well you know
freedom of uh freedom of the press
should be protected here
stupid stupid idiotic commentary should
be
publicly engaged with and shamed and
embarrassed
right that's another way of kind of
taking and flipping
the the cancel culture on its head and
say like i don't know let people say it
but you know laugh at them you know and
i think
michael brooks was quite good at doing
that actually about a lot of folks
on the right that he engaged with a lot
of uh celebrities
um so i guess that would be my response
right like
it doesn't produce a culture that is
ultimately
able to hold human flaws
in complexity and therefore what is its
real
what is it really doing you know is it
then it just sort of becomes
an another anti-human force in a world
where we really need
a much more regenerative and redemptive
and empathic approach empathy and
compassion can be ruthless sometimes
but i don't think mob mentalities on
twitter
again are a really
stemming from the left they're a
phenomenon that the left has taken on
that's part of neoliberalism
and b you know mobbing people there's
just how can we really defend that
ultimately right so i i would say those
are those are at least two strong
arguments against
really endorsing this phenomenon
wholesale or whole cloth
um but but the response isn't to fight
it and say we shouldn't be doing that to
say like
well we what are we for right we're for
a redemptive regenerative
empathic culture that is fundamentally
pro-human and not anti-human
um can we achieve that through this sort
of collective behavior
you know we should ask that question i
don't think we can right i think we need
a much more
um uh human-oriented attitude but
yeah um and what comes to mind is what
you mentioned young childhood he has
this excellent book uh
in the swarm that talks about that um
yeah so i'll sneak in another question
then we'll go to the question in the
chat
um you talked a little bit about this
the recuperation aspect um and
the white paper i had on medic tribes i
had this this line um
corporations can be woke but they can't
be anti-capital and how this sort of
like neutered the left and you know uh
um a lot of people talk about this
including the the late michael brooks
um so i was wondering how uh if i'm not
too sophisticated of the
the new critiques or conversations
around this but
could you talk a little bit about how uh
corporations are
using cancel culture itself to neuter
the the left
especially kind of the anti-capitalist
aspect of it
yeah this is the strongest critique that
i think has come from the left about
this which is
you know uh using
using um uh this this new especially
this
year with um uh deangelo's book on white
fragility has been sort of a
contesting point matt taibbi had that
piece um
um adolf reed had some interesting
comments on that piece and so did
michael brooks
um and part of the issue here is again
looking at what what is the ultimate aim
and function of this if this simply
becomes an armature of
um the corporate sector to like
make mindfulness appropriate a thing
that
was genuinely interested in economic
and racial justice right it could be
genuinely transformative
um and appropriate and sort of declaw it
to allow it to fit into the armistice of
corporatism and capitalism and this we
see this everywhere and this is again
um the reason why uh i see this is such
an
endemic phenomenon is that we can look
at the intellectual dark web and see the
same thing
the same argument watered against um
uh jordan peterson's work right which is
cleaning your own room in a neoliberal
world
is a great argument like that's that's
fantastic yes like
don't blame it on any kind of social
exterior issues
it's only about cleaning up your own
interior your mess your own subjectivity
and having a better
um responsible orientation towards life
don't worry about what the corporations
are doing that's a slippery slope to the
um the progressive leftist attitude that
just wants everything handed to it and
wants a perfect ideal
world right so that is a great argument
too
but this is this is what i mean that
this sort of neoliberal structure
um in that sort of uh uh
cthulhu-like capacity this sort of
tentacular capacity can take things on
the left and the right and appropriate
them for itself right
so we that is why we really need that
literacy to kind of
help us navigate this and make the
critiques where they're necessary
um so yeah i think you know having
having a corporate uh woke
culture going forward where this is just
going to be part of
um you know the congress taking taking a
knee
but then actively legislatively and
economically
you know not voting for racial justice
in terms of you know where they're
putting their money where the where the
power is going right
where the institutional and structural
redu redistribution isn't happening
right but if they can symbolically do
this then somehow
you know replicated i think this that is
very dangerous
um so if anything though i would say
like and i take this as a friendlier
because a lot of people on the left are
doing a lot of good work with this and
they are kind of
they're trying to bring it in right um
they're trying to bring in
the anti-capitalists or uh the more
structural critiques
um within race and identity politics um
but maybe they're getting co-opted so i
would like i would like to say like
on the left i want to work with them you
know i want to be able to say like
well let's see if we can like trojan
horse this too
right like maybe but we need to be bold
we need to keep that class and economic
literacy
at the forefront of what we're thinking
so when we show up to the starbucks
board about like
you know black lives matter um there are
some people who are also
very well trained and thinking about
okay how can we make starbucks
more worker owned you know like how
could we actually
transform this economic structure
um and use this as a sort of trojan
horse for doing so
and i think that requires this is the
critique back on the left that requires
a lot of synthesis and coalition
building because again when we said
30 or 40 years the erosion of class
politics has
left the left in this sort of culture
oriented position
using the weapons and the tools and the
and the media that it has
to make inroads but not with a
not with a kind of truly you know power
oriented
michael used to call it a machiavellian
spirituality deep
compassion but we have to be ruthless
towards systems we have to know them
very well
and we have to make inroads where we can
um
i think that's what's missing and maybe
that's what we've seen kind of
um fall back on or or the the issues
right now with black lives matter a few
months on have been like
where does this really go from here you
know um
are we really going to just let congress
argue about that
where is our organizing and labor power
here because that is integral to
racial justice and vice versa
yeah that's a great response um
so uh we'll go to uh lisa
i copied and pasted your question uh
below if you could uh
mute yourself and read it to uh jeremy
will you still hear lisa
yeah sorry um i'm here
i think i have a new question uh based
on what jeremy just said sorry i was
camera off
um what i mean i had i wanted to build
on ron and
jay i's point is the left right frame
obscuring our ability to encounter the
various splinters on the left the reason
i
said that jeremy is ma and maybe i'd
like to pick up on
the question that comes to mind after
what you just said
is those wedges you know
really knowing the system um
i think there's something tacit in this
conversation about
um to take
a certain position toward the
like admittedly these are effects these
are
ephemeral effects of um you know
canceled culture is just
uh effects in a much bigger system and
we don't need to you know double down on
those and
add to the hysteria and the polarization
how would you think about for example
uh you made the point that yet um
i would you know i would use the new the
term the new left
what how would what would it look like
for the new left to i don't really want
to use the word ally because it's
um obscured but what would it look for
that like today for the new left to
find a sliver of common ground with say
adolf reed
yeah that's a good question and this is
an example i think of
the the problems like the in-house
problems on the left
which is this um perceived divide
between
class reductionists right and then
identity politics they're seen as
split whereas the history you mentioned
the new left uh
the history of the new left since the
1960s
those two questions those two struggles
class and race were very integral to
each other
very complex very nuanced approaches
where you know you know one theorist may
have leaned one way or the other
but that was held together we really
have seen
the bifurcation even happen on the left
which is a problem right that's
that's why um to take the kind of
consciousness studies orientation or
integral approach to this is
okay this is a real problem that even
and even in a um
a body of work in literature and a
history of different
movements and traditions uh even there
that understand
that the commodification of the human
being and the
atomization of culture is a problem that
we need to overcome
and they have a literacy about that even
they are
undone by those same forces of hyper
fragmentation
which is again why i think the left
can't
supersede this without an integrative
approach without really
getting into that tertiary or that third
form of literacy which is that
okay we need to get into the
phenomenology of this we need certain
practices that help us get
out of hyper polarization or fixed
particular you know identity fight
infighting online
like what kind of practices
both social and individual can help um
um be a kind of corrosive against
atomization right that can be
integrative that can cultivate
compassion right
and that's one of the things uh michael
brooks and i were talking about
uh in terms of you know moving forward
uh on the left
after uh one hell of a year of of
uh political movements bernie's campaign
seeming like it was about to win here in
the united states and then completely
um rubber banding the other way there's
there was a lot of
failures there were a lot of gains there
was a lot of awakening there's a lot of
problems and there's a lot of divides so
it's like where do we go from here and
this is more of a question of the left
but i think it also applies to anybody
which is
what are the techniques that help us
overcome hyper fragmentation and
atomization they can't just be
you know reading leftist literature
leftists have been doing that that
hasn't necessarily worked right that's
only part of the literacy
so i do think we need the via
contemplativa
we do need practices of presence and
empathy and compassion
and we do need to bring these into these
kinds of conversations
um because i do think you know
mindfulness has been sort of
depending on how we create and architect
the environment for these practices
um will also kind of
mold or frame how they how they come out
right so if we create
mindfulness and we say oh this will help
you work better and you could become
more present and you
feel less stressed those are the
outcomes then like yeah you're gonna get
like a kind of a docile uh quasi
quasi calm worker in an environment
where nothing's actually changed
but if we in frame these practices and
modalities
as radical things like if you really
want to become radically
present then you will have no no
interest in continuing this culture of
atomization and your own
endeavors creative social and just your
mere presence
are or uh um not anti but it's for the
human and it's for the more than human i
mentioned the post human is this turn i
don't want to get into too many complex
academic jargon phrases but what i mean
for the sake of this conversation is is
the
openness to ecological and and complex
thought that we need
is through this ability to achieve
via contempliva to reclaim temporics
to reclaim social and inter-subjective
spaces
and to say no to like i don't want
atomization i don't want to go on
twitter and
fire up my twitter and take somebody
down and these great
these great like sharp shooting tweets
like we all will make mistakes but
we need to be thinking about this
looping it back to the environmental
as well like what are the environments
that were facilitating these
conversations how can they actually be
radical
and integrative um and again that
doesn't just
apply to the left i think this is a
question everybody
is needs to be thinking about in their
own domains
i don't know if that directly answered
your question but
thank you lisa dylan you had a question
i
pasted it below for you if you're going
to mute yourself and
uh read it to jeremy
uh yeah um so
if cancer in part a function of the
mediums we're using for public discourse
right now
how can we mitigate that um would
efforts to improve rhetoric and
emotional literacy
fit into the spectrum of platforms we're
using
today and i'm asking this i'm interested
in
the potential of things like for example
the stoa
and letters.wiki to kind of
improve our public discourse as we go
forward
thanks yeah that's a great question
you know i i would say like we're at
this point where
like this is just beginning to be a
conversation and it may be
it took the pandemic for us to all be
stuck online
seeing the the the potential and the
pitfalls
of completely replacing you know human
to human contact with the prosthetic of
social media
that like oh there's a lot of limits to
this right so
um yes i think any kind of modalities
and practices and practice spaces
that have different techniques you
mentioned rhetoric and emotional
literacy i think those are great ideas
um i would love to see just more
concrete practices in terms of what
you're looking at
um whatever you know part of like the
integral
response i think is is getting a sense
of coherence about what we're for
not just what we're against and then
developing the techniques that
that move towards that or help achieve
that in some way
so those could be two mentioned via
contemplativa is another one
you know this whole idea in my next book
um fragments of an integral future
futurism i'm talking about reclaiming
time and presence
as a sort of radical openness that i was
just mentioning i think
some kind of practice or praxis in which
we are
using theory in a container of other
modalities
together integrally can be very powerful
and i don't think there will be single
answers i think
what would be great to see is if the
stoa was a platform
and i think it is uh to an extent
that is exploring these different
modalities and seeing what sticks and
what's working right
because part of what i think this
integral turn is is really kind of
embracing what nora bateson talks about
like mutual learning and symmetry
right so this is an open-ended learning
and mutual learning process that we're
all trying to explore together
so feedback for each other
experimentation right um and innovation
and then sharing you know like
let other communities pop up that are
in-house or in a city
um uh halfway across the world
um that are also exploring these things
because
when we're talking about liberalism and
late capitalism and the climate crisis
and then we're also talking on the
the sub-layer of that is the
perspectival crisis that gepsor talks
about the crisis of consciousness
this is a world crisis that like we need
to be building these mesh works of
mutual learning
to figure out to solve together right to
overcome together
so yeah i would just say wholeheartedly
yeah that's great
that's awesome um and it looks like
rebel wisdom just
uh released a video with john verviki
myself talking about some of the
research
uh that we're doing with the psychology
of practice and conversational
modalities that we're experimenting here
with the stoa so i put that in the chat
so many good questions we're not gonna
get to all of them but maybe we can
sneak in one or two more uh
maggie you just had a really good
question if you can unmute yourself and
ask it to
jeremy yeah sure thank you so much for
that
excellent um overview um i've really
enjoyed the integral left
kind of systemic structural critique
which is how i've always understood and
learned about the left
and i think yeah i appreciate that
modernist neoliberal laugh
and how that distinguishes from i think
how
kinds of cultures commonly critiqued my
question is around
that kind of integral left aspiration
and i'm hearing you
emphasize kind of collective spiritual
consciousness
this kind of oneness between different
identities and also class and economic
equity and structural equity and i feel
like that
fundamentally contradicts some of the
more traditional conservative
you know peterson right wing values of
make your bed pull yourself up by your
bootstrap
and if you work hard you can earn a
million dollars and that's not morally
and ethically
incompatible with the system and so i'm
just curious
how you can really transcend and include
both those things because they feel
fundamentally incompatible and i'm just
struggling
to reconcile the both and within these
two
ways of understanding
canceled culture and broader critiques
of integrating the left and right
political
being sure great question and it's
something that comes up
um in a recent conversation with uh
jason snyder
and jared james and we were talking with
them uh on
growingdown podcast and it's this
question of where
you know in this in this sort of
thematic
of the emergent integral left and how
you know where the where the coherencies
of the integral of the a perspective of
the world
um seemed to be friendlier to
leftist positions of reclaiming the
common
social redis social and structural
redistribution even like in gepser in
1949 he was talking about
uh the restructuration of power the
supersession of patriarchy
um so he was thinking this is quite
quite a big overturning
and so how do these how do these
emergent themes reconcile with
more conservative principles of
individualism and i think
to some degree the transcendent include
or perhaps
the uh maybe a better metaphor than
transcendent include would be
borrowing from lynne margus margulis and
donna haraway's symbiogenesis
in which there are certain functions
that will always exist and need to
persist
such as individualism personal
subjectivity
sovereignty autonomy but they exist
within a larger
relationship and they exist because of
that ecological relationship
right that the individual arises from
the collective and vice versa
so seeing them more as a continuum
rather as an
antithesis um to collectivity or
progressive values
i think is helpful right like we don't
want to eliminate individuality we don't
want to eliminate personal
responsibility
it's recognizing like a healthier left
is not
and this doesn't always happen right
because they're the back and forth is
always going on
but a healthier left is recognizing that
individuals are individuals
within a rhizomatic strata of becoming
right that that you are a cell within
this larger organism
and you have your own domain of
individuality and autonomy but you have
it because
of everything that has coalesced to
allow you to become and have that
freedom
right that agency so and this is
something that margulis talks about
quite a bit in her
her biology or talked about um the
autonomy and the agency of a single
organism
is tremendously important for the
evolution of all the organisms the
evolution of
life what a cell decides to do what what
a cell decides to do with its own agency
its own subjectivity
is just as important as the more
reductive
let's say collective forces of this
random genetic mutation etc there's
epigenetic there's creative there's
agentic elements right
so i would kind of i would kind of see
the right and in this regard as sort of
the agentic
elements of our own subjectivity our own
uniqueness right
our ability to kind of go off on our own
do our own thing that can exist to an
extent
right but obviously if you cut off the
individual from the whole
then you don't have the individual
anymore you lose the the conditions that
create
that person standing up with their back
straight
right and that's the side the kind of
thing that i that i heard quite a bit
um i talked about with brooks as well
during the whole peterson
uh it's popularity explosion that uh
cleaning your room and making sure your
you were taken care of
um is really kind of only half the
equation the other half
is like the individual is also impressed
upon by their society so if their
society is sick
if there's social phenomena that create
illness um that creates certain mental
illness etc
depression these aren't just individual
things
they have to you have to see it as a
continuum so i guess that's how i would
see it that
they aren't antithetical so much as they
have a relationship to the whole and
they arise because of the hole
right and i think maybe this wouldn't be
a left position um
this would just be a human position to
see that
mobius strip of individual collective is
like this is how evolution works this is
how any
being is an individual being this is how
any being is a collective being is this
mobius strip of individuality and
collectivity
agency and then these you know these
forces that press upon us and mold us a
certain way
it's the sort of dynamic downs
any follow-up maggie or any comments
um i mean i really appreciate that that
view of um yeah it's a spectrum and it's
it's kind of embedded within more and
more emergent pools or collective
emergence
i think i'm just still confused about
the structural design of that
like to reconcile the structural
you know incentivization of economic
development and the collective
spiritual consciousness oneness um
especially when we have existing
socioeconomic inequality that is so
deeply
interconnected with race and you know
all of these identity
politics that is material and real so
i'm just more curious i think about the
system i critique all that and that
philosophical
conception it's really helpful sure
yeah i'll just briefly say i know we're
at the top of the hour that um
that they think there are like concrete
models that we can look at and think
about adapting
in places like the united states
obviously um but i really like thomas
bjorkman's whole
um bildung or
the the sort of self-realization process
that a collectivist society
you know a more socialist-oriented
society actually
endorses and puts into practice so
individual realization becomes very
important to the well-being
of the whole and they have institutions
that put that into place
so when we're talking about things like
health care we're talking about social
equity
and the policies that put that into
place those aren't just for the
collective they also become extremely
significant for the health and
resilience of
and the self-actualization right
spiritual or otherwise of the of the
individual
my my buddy ryan mcaday is on a kick
with this kind of synthesis
of uh uh what these socialist countries
are doing and bjorkman's work
and maybe some ways to translate that
into the kind of rugged individualism of
of american culture
right because i think that is a problem
we sort of see ourselves as sort of
going alone
um and but i would also say that i think
part of that
um part of that rugged individualism
even though it's been sort of an
integral component of american culture
the american imaginary it's also
um been hyper actualized by
again the 35 40 years of of um
the erosion of class and labor politics
um you know uh
in that documentary i shared in that uh
in my article
that minidoc uh one of the interesting
things i learned
was you know when you joined a a union
for your job
your union took you to school and made
you learn about uh
how politics how economics work what
your role is in the union what to look
out for
on the job etc so you know in terms of
like really practical institutional
policies we've lost quite a lot of that
social cohesion
over the past 40 years which again is
part of that problem of atomization
so yeah i think i think there's a lot we
need to talk about
and obviously we can't get to it all
here and
i don't know all of the solutions that
are emerging on the on the left but this
is this is the
like this is the question like okay the
left is waking up again
what do we do how do we organize how do
we actually get traction
with policy um consciousness raising
and organization right how do we
actually have power that's the question
and i think that's sort of where you're
getting to in terms of like the
conservative bent and then also this new
kind of revival of
socialism or leftism or collectivism
that is
re-emerging and integrating again but i
would look to the history of socialism
in the united states
um as just great examples of historical
precedence i think
um harvey k has some great writing on
that um richard wolff
has some great writing on understanding
socialism and
another book um democracy at work so
yeah
very cool thank you maggie um yeah we're
past the top of the hour uh that was an
excellent uh
talk jeremy and a q a um is there
anything you'd like to leave us
off with before we close out just uh
just to thank you
um an invitation to continue to explore
these questions um on what a um
you know again the left is an ally here
in
exploring what an integrative
post-atomized
you know coherent future culture looks
like
they have important tools for the
toolkit and let's collaborate
let's build it let's explore last thing
would just be
feel free to join me on patreon i'll
post it in the chat um i host little
zoom calls and we have a book club
uh every month or so and we have deep
dives like this so
yep excellent yeah thanks so much
my friend i'd love to have you back and
hopefully i don't have to release
another ridiculous uh
art piece to get you back um so a couple
of announcements uh
if you um there's two events coming up
this evening
the stoa one is the ultra mindset with
uh
travis macy so think of david goggins
but like a cool indie version of david
goggins he's a
endurance athlete ultra marathon runner
and he's going to talk about his eight
core principles for
for success and building that kind of
mindset and then um
we have ralph kelly after that uh tyson
wagner are you still here
yes you are i'm here can you plug it
um yes rake will be here talking about
play
and meaning making rafe leads retreats
called return to the source
where he gathers groups of people
together in nature in a beautiful place
and teaches natural movement
participation
with the natural world and he's going to
talk to us about play
and uh thanks peter thanks jeremy see
you guys later beautiful
so the travis events at 6 30 pm eastern
time today and then the rafe event is at
8 00 p.m
eastern time uh today let me just double
check that
8 30 p.m eastern time uh and if you'd
like to support the stoa
um you can go to our patreon page all
our events are free and i'd like to
continue to be so but it'll be great to
have your your support
uh for for us doing what we're doing
here so
yeah i think that's it uh thank you
jeremy thank you everyone for coming out
today